You have character animation data with issues with your feet that are sliding on the ground and you want to fix those
Hi, I'm Jerome and today we will be looking at the footscade cleanup for motion capture editing a paper from 2002
As always the first thing I would do is importing the
All the libraries I would need inside of my notebook and I will load my characters as I'm doing
every time. Now one thing I would do on top of this is creating a new mesh and
that mesh is just a little target that I can place on the ground to display
where I want to do some contacts. So just creating a new mesh. Now I would need
to change a little my skeleton because the paper itself assumes that you have
this skeleton. Basically it needs to have an eel joint and a ball joint and
and that's because they need to be able to know where the ground is relative to your ankle
and in my skeleton I don't have those bones yet
so what I would do is inject the new bones here inside of my skeleton as child of the foot
and now that I have this I actually have the same skeleton as what they want to have
And now that I have the skeleton, I can actually load my animation on top.
And what I would do is that I would load the animation once as the animation I'm retargeting,
and that's the reason why my feet would be sliding.
If you check the video about the animation data, I explain why that's happening.
It's because my character has different proportions, so the feet would be sliding.
And now what I will do also is I will import the original animation data, as is, with the
character squashed, but with the actual position from the animation data.
And the reason why I'm doing this is because the paper itself is there to fix your feet
on the ground when you know that the feet should be locked.
it doesn't help you to detect when you want to lock the feet. It's allow you to compute it properly
but not the when. So luckily enough for me, the data from the Lafan database is actually extremely
stable. So I will load the animation as the original data and I will use just the position
of the bones and the speed of the bones to know when I want to get the contacts and when I wanted
to move. So what I do is that I load twice the animation and then my character is a little bigger
than the one from the data. So I'm moving the character up a little so there's a little bit
of the ground, otherwise the feet are really in the ground. Now, as I said, I want to compute
when I want to get the contacts. And what I will do is that I would build a big buffer
with all the contacts for every frame. So I have a buffer which has the frame count
and then four values and those four values are the left heel, left ball, right heel, right ball
contacts basically when it's static or not and I'm just using the extract feed contacts which is
just using an heuristic on the speed and I'm checking the the bone itself and if the bones
from the left is moving faster than 0.04 cm per second or something. I don't remember exactly
the speed itself but basically if the speed is lower than that I'm assuming that there is a
contact otherwise it's moving. Now what I do after is actually smoothing the signal a little
because it happens that you have a contact and then for one frame it turns off the contact
and the kind of stuff. And I want to make sure that if I have just one or two frames that says
I'm not in contact, it's probably mean that is just a bug in the detection. So I just want to
smooth the signal and make sure that I will always have at least three frames of contacts.
And that's what these little smooth functions are doing here. So now I can have
my contact timing and then we could display exactly what this means here and
so what I have is the animation moving and then you could see when I've
detected that I want to have a contact and that's thanks to the original motion
and you can see that the feet themselves are sliding compared to where the
contacts are. At the bottom I have the signal on off for left heel, left ball,
right heel, right ball basically. Now that we know what the contacts, when the
contacts should happen, I can actually go through the paper and see what the
algorithm is. So for the footskate cleanup methods, they basically have five
different phases. And the first phase is to determine the position of each constraint.
So to compute the constraint position, what the algorithm will do is compute it one bone at a time
and what you do is that if you detect that the heel should be static, what you do is you go
forward in time and then go for L1 frames. So it's a constant. You could change and tweak
how long that window of frames will be. But then what you do is that you go forward in time and
you check every frame as long as they also says that they are all in constraint. You take the
the average of all those positions so you get all the positions take the average
and you drop it on the ground to get the contact on the ground and for every
other frames if they say I mean I'm in constraint and the frame before was
already in constraint basically I already competed the average so I just keep
the same constraint as the one from the frame before. You do this for each of
your bones and the only thing that will change is if for instance the ball says
I'm in constraint for the first time in this frame you will check if the heel
was already constrained if it's the case basically you re-project the distance
of the ball so you don't change the relation between heel ball the distance
between the heel ball so it means that if you complete the heel first you put
the heel on the ground, and then the ball says,
now I'm also constrained.
You put the ball on the ground
and you move it to keep the same distance.
If you do the opposite,
it means that you get the ball first on the ground.
By the time you hit the heel on the ground,
you actually move the heel to realign the distance also.
So that's what I'm doing here.
I'm computing the contact position.
And the difference I have is so I've used the L1
as a 10 frame. And I will build a big buffer with all my constraint position buffer. So
it takes all the frame counts, the position for the left, left, right, left, right balls,
and then the XYZ position for the space. And I'm doing the entire buffer at once because
basically I know the length of my animation, I can compute the entire animation in one
the algorithm basically says that you could do it this way or you could do
frame by frame and recompute everything or you could just try to build a bunch
of buffers that have just the right sizes. It's easier for me to implement this
paper by just saying well I'm doing the entire animation in one go. So I get a
constraint buffer, position buffer and see basically that's what I'm
I'm checking here, I'm checking if the constraint was,
if the object was already constrained the frame before.
In that case, I just keep the same position.
Otherwise, I move forward L1 frame
and I do the average and I drop it on the ground.
And I do it for each and also
reprojecting the distance.
And I do it for each left heel, left ball and so on.
So now that I've compute this,
I can display what I will have here.
And basically now, it's the same as before,
except that the position you could see here
for each target, they actually properly match where
I will want them as the average of all the positions
and basically the distance between heel and ball
are respected every time.
The second part of the algorithm now is to compute the ankle position and rotation you
will want to apply because of those constraints.
Again, to compute that ankle position and rotation, you have several cases that can
happen and the the first case we will cover basically is the case when we have a double
constraint so basically the heel and the ball are constrained that means that now we could
actually compute exactly where the ankle should be because that's the the simplest
case I have a fully constrained foot I can complete compute the ankle the orientation
of the ankle and the position of the ankle. Now if you have a single constraint, so meaning that
maybe you only have the heel that is constrained or maybe you only have the ball that is constrained,
the only thing you have to do is not compute any reorientation of the ankle, you only want to move
move the ball, move the ankle to match the right heel, the right ball or the right heel
position depending on the context.
So if you have a double constraint, you actually compute the position and orientation, and
you have a single constraint, you only move the position.
But that would work if you only have that single case.
So if you only have always a single constraint
or always double constraint, now you
need to be able to transition from a single constraint up
to a double constraint and all that kind of stuff.
And that's what this explanation here is.
It's about the fact that if, for instance, you
compute a single constraint and you move your heel
and goes where you want it, and then the frame after is
double constraint, you will pop in that right position instantly. What you want to do instead
is when we compute the actual angle for the angle, we don't save that information as an
absolute value. We don't remember that it's exactly where we want the foot to be. We always
compute those values as an offset compared to what the animation is. So if my animation
says that my foot was here and I computed this position, I keep that information of
offsets. I would want to correct on the ankle. And then if I come from a single
constraint, I can propagate that offsets back in time and I can linearly blend that offset off.
So what it means that if my constraint is here and my foot was here, the offset is that angle.
And so what I will do is that the frame before, I will also reapply that offset a little,
but a little less and then the frame before I still add that offset but a little less so first
thing you do is that you rotate the ankle back in time you rotate the ankle and then you move the
foot and it's the same if you have a double constraint and you reach a single constraint
the same way you add that offsets and then you move the foot back and then add that offset and
and then move your foot back.
And you do it back in time and forward in time.
And then if you have that weird case
when you actually go from double constrain,
back double constrain,
you need to cross over that information.
And that's the third case here.
So again, ankle position and the rotation.
So I will have my buffer for the ankle rotation
and the buffer for the ankle position
for both left and right and the first thing I compute is the compute the double constraints.
So again, that's easy because then I can just compute the constraint and save that information
inside of my buffer. And if I have to compute the single constraint, what happens is we check
if you have a single constraint, we then go back in time to see if we come from a double
constraint. If it's the case, I do the slabs. I'm lapping the amount of error I was doing
because of the rotation. In the opposite way, if I will be reaching a double constraint,
Then I also slurping that stuff and then the third case when I come from and go back to
I'm slurping the two slurps together and then you get that final result. So that's basically what this
Is doing and the only thing you have here is that we formula for the alpha and that comes from the paper also
Dave
They hear so basically that's how they smooth
the transition. They don't do purely linear correction. They do easy and easy out
correction and that's what the formula allows you to have. And so I can compute
my constraints and now what I will have is my buffer here. I can display it and
you could see where I would want the ankle to be and that's basically where
every time you see there is a constraint that's actually where I want the
ankle to be when we compute it. So we've computed the orientation and the
position of the ankle. We can go to the next step and the next one is to
compute the root placement and the root placement basically means that for
instance imagine that you try to fix the foot and you put it really far away
away from where the the hips can be, then you will have the issue that the foot cannot reach
the constraint you wanted to fix. So what we will do is that we will move the the hips so
we will make sure that the foot can always reach the position we want to do.
And the root placement, well basically again it depends on the the case and how you want to
compute it. If you only have one foot that is constrained, you could only, and it's too far,
you could only move the root in the direction of the foot you're pulling. But if both feet are
constrained, you actually need to compute the position here of where, by pulling on both feet,
where the hips should be and that's basically at the intersection of both spheres so if imagine
you have your foot and then you draw a sphere that is the size of your leg and you do that for
the second one you have two spheres and that means you have one point in the middle where you could
put the hips that make sure that both legs can reach the position if the hips is at that spot
so that's how you do this and basically again to avoid having your root that just pulls
one frame when suddenly you cannot reach what they do is that they average the position
they average the the correction they will put on the roots along a bunch of frames
so this is what we do here in the root position we try to compute the offset compare both legs
If the distance does not match and then
Average the position of all those roots and I have a buffer so I will have a buffer of the
The root position now I would want to have
In my case I can display where I want the hips to be
Basically it won't change much because I'm actually never pulling the legs further than what the character is because my character is actually bigger
that what the original animation was, so I will never have the need to pull that route.
Now, because of the average, you're not sure that you will always be able to reach that position,
but that's not an issue, it will be fixed by the next step anyway.
The next step is to be able to actually compute the IK. The way they have implemented that is
to go through these steps. You do compute the angle thanks to the fact that the legs in this
case will be a triangle and then you could compute the angle you need for that triangle.
So they do it in several paths, so you get the original pose, you don't move anything
on that pose, then you change the knee angle and that's by computing this formula here.
It's basically computing the angle thanks to the length of both legs and the length
of the targets you're trying to reach.
So you basically compute the triangle and you try to compute the angle you will have
at the knee.
And then when you computed that angle, you rotate the knee and now that you have rotated
the knee, you could see the distance you have between where your foot would be and where
your target should be.
And you could rotate the entire leg to make sure that you are aligned with the foot.
you realign the ankle to match what the ankle target was, and the last step they do and they
actually stretch the leg. And why do they stretch the leg? Because of two things. The first thing is
that if you remember when we moved the route, we said that we were doing the average, which means
that it's possible that your route is still too far for the leg to actually be able to reach it.
So you do need to be able to stretch the leg
because of the smoothing we did on the roots.
And the second thing that's,
it's when we try to do IK on that kind of stuff
with the legs that's really close to being stretched.
What happened in IKs is that
if your leg is really close to be straight,
being straight or not will actually change the distance here really a little.
So you might try to reach a point that is one or two centimeters away and then it will be really
visible on your knee. Usually we call that a knee pop. It's something that you could see when you
do IK. You see that knee that moves really fast because it just goes from here to here
just because it had to close a really small distance so what they do is that they
detect that the ankle is really close to be straight and they allow the leg to stretch
in that case so they can avoid that knee pops and give more times for the for the knee to be straight
And I would do the same except I will do a bit differently that the paper is doing it.
I will not stretch the actual leg, I will just lock the angle of the knee and I will
just stretch by moving the foot relative to the leg, meaning that basically that the formation
is absorbed by my ankle and it's really not visible when you have a small
distance seeing that the the ankle in changing in size is not more visible
than trying to stretch the entire leg and moving knees ankle and everything so
just by doing this I mean it's it's enough and so what I'm doing is this
the the the part that you have here all the Arcos formula it's the one I'm
doing here, so you are preparing all the different lengths compared to the distance, computing the
vector, computing the arcos. And then I'm taking that arcos, and what I'm doing is that I'm
putting it through a polynomial. I'll show you the polynomial later. Basically, just to make
make sure that my ankle would avoid having that knee pop,
and then I can compute the angle,
I can rotate the knee,
I can recompute the position of the knee,
I can rotate the entire leg,
compute the global position of the foot,
and then put back my ankle.
So it's all the step of the paper,
and I do the same for the right leg and all kind of stuff.
And just to show you what that weird polynomial is,
It's just this.
So basically, we could see it's really close
of a straight line.
And that's, an arc cost basically means
that it's the inverse of the Christmas.
So at minus one, I have 180 degrees.
So my leg is really straight.
And what I do is I have something
that is nearly mapping, except here at the end.
So the blue will be the arc cost value.
and my orange one is the functions that I'm computing.
You see that basically that means that if my leg
should have been a straight line with 180 degrees,
I'm just keeping a little angle in there.
And that it goes further.
And so you will always be able to make sure
that you always keep an angle.
And it's a smooth angle here.
So at least I never have a straight leg
and I'm never stretching.
So it's not exactly how they were doing it,
but it's one way of not having the knee pop, let's say.
I can compute my IK, so at least I have something to show.
And now I can render what they had here.
And then you could see that when the constraint are on,
Basically, my legs are properly placed,
my foot are properly placed where the ankle wanted to be,
except that you could see pops every time
my animation turns on and off.
You get that pop for every constraint.
And so that's actually the last step of the algorithm.
is the final processing.
And what the final processing does is,
well, realizing that we've computed every ankle position
and all of that as an offset
compared to where the animation was.
And if you remember what we've moved from single to double,
or double to single, we smooth out that information.
And basically what the final processing
would be doing is the same thing it would say okay now we could detect every
time a constraint is done on and off and we could also propagate the the the
offsets and blend them in and blend them out the same way we did for the
single to double except now we do it for every constraint so check for the for
the ankle, make sure that we turn on and off, and then we blend that information also forward
the same way. And then when we've done this, we can finally do the IK on that solution
instead of doing the IK before doing the final processing. And now what we have is this.
You could see that moving in and out of a constraint now is perfectly smooth because
we smooth out that information.
So we have exactly what we wanted.
And this is one of the way you could fix sliding issues.
If you find this video to be too fast or too slow or not enough in detail, feel free to
comments at the bottom so I know how to adjust for future videos and I will see
you for the next paper.